[
    {
        "question": "Which country's mission successfully demonstrated artificial photosynthesis in space?",
        "options": [
            "United States - Artemis",
            "Russia - Soyuz MS",
            "China - Shenzhou-19",
            "India - Gaganyaan",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "How much funding has been allocated for the Samudrayaan Mission in the Union Budget?",
        "options": [
            "400 crore",
            "500 crore",
            "600 crore",
            "750 crore",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "600 crore"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country will host the BRICS Youth Council Entrepreneurship Working Group Meeting in March 2025?",
        "options": [
            "China",
            "Brazil",
            "India",
            "South Africa",
            "Russia"
        ],
        "answer": "India"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been appointed as the Additional Director General, Directorate General of Foreign Trade (DGFT), as of February 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Anant Swarup",
            "Samar Nanda",
            "Santosh Kumar Verma",
            "Abhinav Gupta",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Marcus Stoinis, who recently announced his retirement from ODIs ahead of the Champions Trophy, represents which country in international cricket?",
        "options": [
            "England",
            "Australia",
            "South Africa",
            "New Zealand",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been awarded the Sahitya Akademi Award 2024 in Dogri literature?",
        "options": [
            "Jitendra Udhampuri",
            "Chaman Arora",
            "Veena Gupta",
            "Sushma Rani",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following groups of sites were newly added as Ramsar sites in India, bringing the total to 89?",
        "options": [
            "Sakkarakottai and Therthangal Bird Sanctuaries (Tamil Nadu), Khecheopalri Wetland (Sikkim), and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)",
            "Harike Wetland (Punjab), Chilika Lake (Odisha), and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)",
            "Chilika Lake (Odisha), Loktak Lake (Manipur), and Sambhar Salt Lake (Rajasthan)",
            "Only Khecheopalri Wetland (Sikkim) and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Sakkarakottai and Therthangal Bird Sanctuaries (Tamil Nadu), Khecheopalri Wetland (Sikkim), and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of NASA's new space telescope set to launch in February 2025, which aims to survey the entire sky in 102 infrared colors?",
        "options": [
            "SPHEREx",
            "James Webb Space Telescope 2.0",
            "Hubble Space Telescope 2.0",
            "Chandra-CRISP X-ray Observatory",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "SPHEREx"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country recently passed strict hate crime laws, imposing a minimum 12-month jail term for public Nazi salutes and up to six years for terror-related hate crimes?",
        "options": [
            "Canada",
            "Australia",
            "Germany",
            "United Kingdom",
            "Japan"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of Zomato's AI-powered, no-code customer support platform designed to help businesses scale their operations?",
        "options": [
            "Zassist",
            "Midget",
            "Nugget",
            "Zai",
            "Pro"
        ],
        "answer": "Nugget"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is India's rank among the top 10 countries most affected by extreme weather events over the last three decades (1993-2023), as per the Climate Risk Index (CRI) published by Greenwatch?",
        "options": [
            "4th",
            "6th",
            "8th",
            "10th",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "6th"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company ranked 2nd globally in the FutureBrand Index 2024, ahead of brands like Apple and Nike?",
        "options": [
            "Google",
            "Samsung",
            "Microsoft",
            "Reliance",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is the richest woman in the world in 2025, according to the Forbes Billionaire List?",
        "options": [
            "Françoise Bettencourt Meyers",
            "Julia Koch",
            "Alice Walton",
            "Jacqueline Mars",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been appointed as the new Chief Election Commissioner (CEC) of India in February 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Sukhbir Singh Sandhu",
            "Vivek Joshi",
            "Rajiv Kumar",
            "Gyanesh Kumar",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization launched the \"Imagine a world with more women in science\" campaign marking the 10-year anniversary of the International Day of Women and Girls in Science.?",
        "options": [
            "UNESCO",
            "UNHCR",
            "International Science Council",
            "International Union of Pure and Applied Physics",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "UNESCO"
    },
    {
        "question": "What technology collaboration between the Ministry of Telecommunications (DoT) and International Telecommunication Union (ITU) was focused on in their recent agreement in February 2025?",
        "options": [
            "5G Connectivity Expansion",
            "Cybersecurity Frameworks",
            "AI-driven Digital Twin Technologies",
            "IoT for Urban Planning",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "AI-driven Digital Twin Technologies"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is set to take oath as the Chief Minister of Delhi after winning the Shalimar Bagh seat in the recent Assembly election?",
        "options": [
            "Rekha Gupta",
            "Vijender Gupta",
            "Harsh Vardhan",
            "Parvesh Verma",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Rekha Gupta"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Government of Tamil Nadu celebrates Thiruvalluvar Day in honor of the poet Thiruvalluvar?",
        "options": [
            "13 January",
            "14 January",
            "15 January",
            "16 January",
            "17 January"
        ],
        "answer": "15 January"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two films led the BAFTA 2025, each winning 4 awards?",
        "options": [
            "Conclave and The Brutalist",
            "Anora and The Brutalist",
            "Conclave and Anora",
            "The Brutalist and The Artist",
            "Conclave and The Artist"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been appointed as the Deputy Secretary in the Department of Expenditure under the Central Staffing Scheme?",
        "options": [
            "Sanjay Malhotra",
            "T.V. Somanathan",
            "Girish Chandra Murmu",
            "Mrithinjai Srikanthan",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Mrithinjai Srikanthan"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) announced that 20 non-banking financial companies have surrendered their certificates of registration. What is the main reason behind the surrender of certificates?",
        "options": [
            "Exit from the financial sector and mergers",
            "Non-compliance with RBI regulations",
            "Low profitability and high debts",
            "Shift to banking operations",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where will the sixth edition of the India-Japan joint military exercise Dharma Guardian 2025 be held?",
        "options": [
            "Tokyo",
            "Sapporo",
            "Osaka",
            "Mount Fuji",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which bank became the first in India to implement compliance for the Digital Personal Data Protection Act (DPDP Act) 2023?",
        "options": [
            "State Bank of India",
            "Axis Bank",
            "HDFC Bank",
            "ICICI Bank",
            "PNB"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was elected as the new Prime Minister of Vanuatu in February 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Stephen Felix",
            "Charlot Salwai",
            "Jotham Napat",
            "Ishmael Kalsakau",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been appointed as the Chief Executive Officer of Standard Chartered India, effective April 1, 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Zarin Daruwala",
            "Deepak Parekh",
            "P D Singh",
            "Aditya Puri",
            "Mohak Singh"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) has penalized Nainital Bank, Ujjivan Small Finance Bank, and Shriram Finance with fines totaling ₹68.1 lakh for non-compliance with various banking regulations. How much was the Nainital Bank fined by the RBI?",
        "options": [
            "₹61.40 lakh",
            "₹6.70 lakh",
            "₹5.80 lakh",
            "₹10.20 lakh",
            "₹15.40 lakh"
        ],
        "answer": "₹61.40 lakh"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the objective of ISRO's development of the world's largest 10-tonne vertical planetary propellant mixer, created in collaboration with the Central Manufacturing Technology Institute?",
        "options": [
            "To improve satellite communication technology",
            "To develop reusable launch vehicles",
            "To manufacture lightweight spacecraft materials",
            "To enhance the production of solid rocket motors",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "To enhance the production of solid rocket motors"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which institution has the Supreme Court appointed to prepare a plan for improving Delhi's green cover?",
        "options": [
            "Forest Research Institute (FRI)",
            "Indian Institute of Forest Management",
            "National Environmental Engineering Research Institute",
            "Central Pollution Control Board",
            "NGT"
        ],
        "answer": "Forest Research Institute (FRI)"
    },
    {
        "question": "China has approved the construction of a deepwater research facility that will be located at a depth of ____________ below the ocean surface in the South China Sea?",
        "options": [
            "2,000 meters",
            "2,500 meters",
            "3,000 meters",
            "3,500 meters",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the indigenous semiconductor chip developed by ISRO and IIT Madras for space-based applications?",
        "options": [
            "SHAKTI",
            "IRIS",
            "CORE",
            "VIKRAM",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "At which port did India's Matsya-6000 submersible successfully complete its wet tests, moving closer to the 500m shallow-water trials by 2025 as part of the Samudrayan Project under the Deep Ocean Mission?",
        "options": [
            "Chennai Port",
            "Visakhapatnam Port",
            "Mumbai Port",
            "Kattupalli Port",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the theme of the first-ever Regional Dialogue on the Global Coalition for Social Justice, scheduled for February 24-25, 2025, in New Delhi?",
        "options": [
            "\"Sustainable Development through Green Business\"",
            "\"Innovation for Social Justice and Equality\"",
            "\"Empowering Communities for Global Progress\"",
            "\"Responsible Businesses for Inclusive & Sustainable Societies\"",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "\"Responsible Businesses for Inclusive & Sustainable Societies\""
    }
]